The global challenge that I want to talk to you about today
التحدي العالمي الذي أرغب في التحدث لكم عنه اليوم
rarely makes the front pages.
نادرا ما يكتب عنه في الصفحات الأولى.
It, however, is enormous
لكنه، رغم هذا، ضخم
in both scale and importance.
على مستوى الحجم والأهمية.
Look, you all are very well traveled;
حسنا، أنتم جميعا سافرتم كثيرا;
this is TEDGlobal after all.
هو مؤتمر TED العالمي بالنهاية.
But I do hope to take you to some places
لكنني آمل أن أخذكم لبعض الأماكن
you've never been to before.
التي لم تمضوا لها من قبل.
So, let's start off in China.
إذن، دعونا نبدأ في الصين.
This photo was taken two weeks ago.
هذه الصورة التقطت منذ أسبوعين مضيا.
Actually, one indication is that little boy on my husband's shoulders
في الواقع، الدليل على هذا أن الولد الصغير على كتفيّ زوجي
has just graduated from high school.
للتو تخرج من الثانوية هذا العام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But this is Tiananmen Square.
ولكن هذه الصورة كانت في ساحة تيانانمن.
Many of you have been there. It's not the real China.
العديد منكم زارها. ليست الصين الحقيقية.
Let me take you to the real China.
دعوني آخذكم للصين الحقيقية.
This is in the Dabian Mountains
هذه هي جبال دابيان.
in the remote part of Hubei province in central China.
في الجزء الأقصى من مقاطعة هوبيي في مركز الصين.
Dai Manju is 13 years old at the time the story starts.
داي مانجو هي في الثالثة عشرة من العمر عندما بدأت الحكاية.
She lives with her parents,
هي تعيش مع أبويها،
her two brothers and her great-aunt.
أخويها الإثنين وعمة والدها.
They have a hut that has no electricity,
لديهم كوخ لاتتوفر به الكهرباء،
no running water,
أو الماء الجاري،
no wristwatch, no bicycle.
لا ساعة معصم، لا دراجة.
And they share this great splendor
وهم يشاركون هذا كله
with a very large pig.
مع خنزير كبير.
Dai Manju was in sixth grade when her parents said,
داي مانجو كانت في الصف السادس عندما قال والداها،
"We're going to pull you out of school
"سنقوم بإخراجك من المدرسة
because the 13-dollar school fees are too much for us.
لأن الثلاثة عشر دولارا رسوم المدرسة هي كثيرة علينا.
You're going to be spending the rest of your life in the rice paddies.
أنت ستقضين باقي حياتك في حقول الأرز
Why would we waste this money on you?"
فلم نضيع النقود بإنفاقها عليك؟"
This is what happens to girls in remote areas.
هذا ما يحدث للفتيات في الأماكن المعزولة.
Turns out that Dai Manju was
تبين أن داي مانجو كانت
the best pupil in her grade.
أفضل طالبة في صفها.
She still made the two-hour trek to the schoolhouse
وهي استمرت في قطع رحلة ساعتين لمقر مدرستها
and tried to catch every little bit of information
وحاولت أن تلتقط أي معلومة لو كانت صغيرة
that seeped out of the doors.
تتسرب من خلف أبواب الفصول.
We wrote about her in The New York Times.
كتبنا عنها في النيويورك تايمز.
We got a flood of donations --
وحصلنا على سيل من التبرعات --
mostly 13-dollar checks
غالبا شيكات بقيمة 13 دولار،
because New York Times readers are very generous
لأن قراء النيويورك تايمز كانوا أسخياء جدا
in tiny amounts
بكميات ضئيلة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
but then, we got a money transfer
ولكن وقتها، قمنا بتحويل الأموال
for $10,000 --
حوالي 10,000 دولار
really nice guy.
من قبل شخص لطيف جدا.
We turned the money over to that man there, the principal of the school.
حولنا النقود لذاك الرجل هناك، ناظر المدرسة.
He was delighted.
وهو ابتهج جدا.
He thought, "Oh, I can renovate the school.
فكر، "أوه، أستطيع أن أجدد بناء المدرسة.
I can give scholarships to all the girls,
أستطيع أن أهب منحا لكل الفتيات".
you know, if they work hard and stay in school.
للفتيات اللاتي يبذلن جهدا دراسيا للبقاء في المدرسة.
So Dai Manju basically
وإذن داي مانجو
finished out middle school.
أنهت المدرسة المتوسطة.
She went to high school.
ذهبت للمدرسة الثانوية.
She went to vocational school for accounting.
ثم لمدرسة مهنية في تخصص المحاسبة.
She scouted for jobs down in Guangdong province in the south.
بحثت عن وظائف في مقاطعة قوانقدونق في الجنوب.
She found a job, she scouted for jobs
وجدت وظيفة، ثم أخذت بالبحث عن وظائف
for her classmates and her friends.
لزميلاتها بالصف وصديقاتها.
She sent money back to her family.
أرسلت النقود لعائلتها.
They built a new house,
بنوا بها منزلا جديدا،
this time with running water,
هذه المرة به ماء صحي،
electricity, a bicycle,
كهرباء، دراجة،
no pig.
وبدون خنزير.
What we saw was a natural experiment.
ما رأيناه كان تجربة طبيعية.
It is rare to get an exogenous investment
من النادر أن نجد استثمارات خارجية
in girls' education.
في مجال تعليم الفتيات.
And over the years, as we followed Dai Manju, we were able to see
وعلى مر الأعوام، بينما كنا نتابع داي مانجو، كنا قادرين على رؤية
that she was able to move out of a vicious cycle
أنها استطاعت الخروج من الحلقة المفرغة
and into a virtuous cycle.
إلى حلقة مثمرة.
She not only changed her own dynamic,
هي لم تغير مصيرها وحسب،
she changed her household, she changed her family, her village.
هي غيرت أوضاع منزلها، غيرت عائلتها، وقريتها نحو الأفضل.
The village became a real standout.
أصبحت القرية نموذجا بارزا.
Of course, most of China was flourishing at the time,
بالتأكيد، أغلب الصين كانت تزدهر في ذاك الوقت،
but they were able to get a road built
ولكنهم تمنكوا من تعبيد طريق
to link them up to the rest of China.
ليربط القرية ببقية الصين.
And that brings me to my first major
وهذا يقودني لأول وأهم
of two tenets of "Half the Sky."
المبدأين المذكورين في كتابي "نصف السماء".
And that is that
وهو أن
the central moral challenge
التحدي الأخلاقي الأساسي
of this century
لهذا القرن
is gender inequity.
هو عدم المساواة بين الجنسين.
In the 19th century, it was slavery.
في القرن التاسع عشر كان العبودية.
In the 20th century, it was totalitarianism.
في القرن العشرين كان الشمولية (النظام السياسي القمعي).
The cause of our time
قضية زمننا هذا
is the brutality that so many people
هي الوحشية التي يعامل بها
face around the world because of their gender.
الكثير من الناس حول العالم بسبب جنسهم.
So some of you may be thinking,
البعض منكم قد يفكر،
"Gosh, that's hyperbole.
"يا إلهي، هذا غلو.
She's exaggerating."
هي تبالغ كثيرا".
Well, let me ask you this question.
حسنا، دعوني اسألكم هذا السؤال.
How many of you think there are more males or more females in the world?
كم منكم يعتقد أن هناك رجال أو نساء أكثر في العالم؟
Let me take a poll. How many of you think there are more males in the world?
دعني استطلع. كم منكم يعتقد أن هناك رجال أكثر في العالم؟
Hands up, please.
ارفعوا ايديكم، لو سمحتم.
How many of you think -- a few -- how many of you there are more females in the world?
كم منكم يعتقد -- القليل-- أن هناك نساء أكثر في العالم؟
Okay, most of you.
حسنا، أغلبكم.
Well, you know this latter group, you're wrong.
تعلمون، أنتم في المجموعة الأخيرة، مخطئون.
There are, true enough,
الواقع أنه، فعليا،
in Europe and the West,
في أوروبا والغرب،
when women and men
عندما يكون للنساء والرجال
have equal access to food and health care,
فرص متساوية للحصول على الغذاء والرعاية الصحية
there are more women, we live longer.
تكون هناك نساء أكثر، نحن نعيش لفترات أطول.
But in most of the rest of the world, that's not the case.
ولكن في غالب باقي دول العالم، الوضع ليس كذلك.
In fact, demographers have shown
في الحقيقة، يوضح علماء الديموغرافيا
that there are anywhere between 60 million
أن هناك تقريبا عدد بين الستين
and 100 million
والمئة مليون
missing females in the current population.
أنثى مفقودين من عدد السكان الحالي (أقل).
And, you know, it happens for several reasons.
و تعلمون، هذا يحدث لعدد من الأسباب.
For instance, in the last half-century,
على سبيل المثال، في الخمسين سنة الماضية
more girls were discriminated to death
عدد الفتيات التي أدى التمييز ضدهم للوفاة
than all the people killed on all the battlefields
يفوق كل عدد الأشخاص الذين قتلوا في كل المعارك
in the 20th century.
في القرن العشرين.
Sometimes it's also because of the sonogram.
أحيانا يكون هذا أيضا بسبب السونوجرام (تصوير الجنين)
Girls get aborted before they're even born
الفتيات يتم إجهاضهم من قبل حتى أن يولدوا
when there are scarce resources.
عندما تكون الموارد عند العائلة شحيحة.
This girl here, for instance,
هذه الفتاة هنا، كمثال،
is in a feeding center in Ethiopia.
هي في مركز تغذية في إثيوبيا.
The entire center was filled with girls like her.
المركز كله كان مليء بفتيات مثلها.
What's remarkable is that her brothers, in the same family,
المميز في الأمر أن أخوتها، في العائلة نفسها،
were totally fine.
كانوا أصحاء تماما.
In India, in the first year of life,
في الهند، في السنة الأولى بعد الولادة،
from zero to one,
من صفر وحتى السنة،
boy and girl babies basically survive at the same rate
الفتى والفتاة بشكل مبدأي يبقيان على قيد الحياة بنفس المعدل
because they depend upon the breast,
لأنهم يعتمدون على الرضاعة،
and the breast shows no son preference.
والثدي لا يبدي أي تفضيل للابن الذكر.
From one to five,
من عمر الواحدة حتى الخامسة،
girls die at a 50 percent higher mortality rate
تموت الفتيات بمعدل وفيات أعلى بخمسين بالمئة
than boys, in all of India.
من الفتيان، في كل أنحاء الهند.
The second tenet of "Half the Sky"
المبدأ الثاني لـ "نصف السماء"
is that, let's put aside the morality of all the right and wrong of it all,
هو أنه، لنضع جانبا الأحكام الأخلاقية لكل ماهو صواب وماهو خاطىء.
and just on a purely practical level,
وفقط على المستوى العملي،
we think that
نعتقد أن
one of the best ways to fight poverty and to fight terrorism
إحدى أفضل الطرق لمكافحة الفقر والقضاء على الإرهاب
is to educate girls
هو أن نعلم الفتيات
and to bring women into the formal labor force.
ونضخ النساء للقوة العاملة.
Poverty, for instance.
الفقر، على سبيل المثال.
There are three reasons why this is the case.
هناك ثلاثة أسباب أدت ليكون هذا هو الوضع.
For one, overpopulation is one of
الأول، الانفجار السكاني كان
the persistent causes of poverty.
ولايزال من الأسباب المستمرة للفقر.
And you know, when you educate a boy,
وتعلمون، عندما تعلم ولدا،
his family tends to have fewer kids,
تميل عائلته لأن يكون فيها أطفال أقل،
but only slightly.
ولكن بشكل طفيف فقط.
When you educate a girl,
عندما تعلم فتاة،
she tends to have significantly fewer kids.
هي تميل لإنجاب أطفال أقل بشكل ملحوظ.
The second reason is
السبب الثاني هو
it has to do with spending.
أن الفقر له علاقة بالإنفاق.
It's kind of like the dirty, little secret of poverty,
هناك مايبدو وكأنه السر الصغير والقذر للفقر،
which is that,
وهو أنه،
not only do poor people
ليس فقط أن الفقراء
take in very little income,
يحصلون على دخل بسيط جدا،
but also, the income that they take in,
ولكن أيضا، الدخل الذي يحصلون عليه،
they don't spend it very wisely,
لا ينفقونه بطريقة حكيمة.
and unfortunately, most of that spending is done by men.
وللأسف، أغلب الإنفاق يقوم به الرجال.
So research has shown,
إذن الأبحاث أظهرت،
if you look at people who live under two dollars a day --
أنكم لو نظرتم للأشخاص الذين يعيشون بأقل من دولارين في اليوم --
one metric of poverty --
وهو أحد مقاييس أو تعريفات الفقر --
two percent of that take-home pay
إثنان بالمئة من هذا المدخول المنزلي
goes to this basket here, in education.
يذهب لهذه السلة والتي تشمل التعليم.
20 percent goes to a basket that is a combination of
20 بالمئة يذهب لسلة تحمل مزيجا من
alcohol, tobacco, sugary drinks --
الكحول، التبغ، المشروبات السكرية (الغازية)
and prostitution and festivals.
دور البغاء والمهرجانات.
If you just take four percentage points
لو أنكم أخذتم فقط أربع نسب مئوية
and put it into this basket,
ووضعتوها في السلة الأخرى،
you would have a transformative effect.
سيكون لديكم أثر جذري.
The last reason has to do
السبب الأخير له علاقة
with women being part of the solution, not the problem.
بكون النساء جزء من الحل، وليس المشكلة.
You need to use scarce resources.
ينبغي أن تستخدموا كافة الموارد القليلة.
It's a waste of resources if you don't use someone like Dai Manju.
إنه هدر للموارد عندما لا تنتفعوا من قدرة شخص مثل داي مانجو.
Bill Gates put it very well
بيل قيتس لخص هذا بشكل جيد جدا
when he was traveling through Saudi Arabia.
عندما كان مسافرا في أنحاء السعودية.
He was speaking to an audience much like yourselves.
هو كان يتحدث لجمهور يشبهكم كثيرا.
However, two-thirds of the way there was a barrier.
ولكن، على بعد ثلثي المسافة كان هناك حاجز.
On this side was men,
على هذا الجانب كان الرجال،
and then the barrier, and this side was women.
ومن ثم بعد الحاجز، على الجانب الآخر كانت النساء.
And someone from this side of the room got up and said,
وشخص من هذا الجانب من الغرفة نهض وقال،
"Mr. Gates, we have here as our goal in Saudi Arabia
"سيد قيتس، هدفنا هنا في المملكة العربية السعودية
to be one of the top 10 countries
أن نكون من أول 10 دول الأهم
when it comes to technology.
حينما يتعلق الأمر بالتقنية.
Do you think we'll make it?"
هل تعتقد أن بإمكاننا تحقيق هذا؟"
So Bill Gates, as he was staring out at the audience, he said,
وبيل قيتس، بينما كان يحدق في الجمهور، قال،
"If you're not fully utilizing half the resources in your country,
"إذا كنتم لا تنتفعون تمام من نصف المصادر التي تملكونها في دولتكم،
there is no way you will get anywhere near the top 10."
فإنه من المستحيل أن تكونوا في أي مركز قريب من العشر الأوائل".
So here is Bill of Arabia.
وإذن إليكم بيل الجزيرة العربية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So what would some of the specific challenges
إذن ما الذي ستكون عليه
look like?
بعض التحديات الدقيقة والخاصة؟
I would say, on the top of the agenda
سأقول، على أول القائمة
is sex trafficking.
يأتي الإتجار بالجنس.
And I'll just say two things about this.
وأنا سأقول شيئين فقط عن هذا الموضوع.
The slavery at the peak of the slave trade
حينما كانت تجارة العبيد في القمة
in the 1780s:
في ثمانينات القرن الثامن عشر:
there were about 80,000 slaves
كان هناك ما يقارب 80,000 عبد
transported from Africa to the New World.
نقلوا من أفريقيا نحو العالم الجديد.
Now, modern slavery:
الآن، العبودية الحديثة:
according to State Department rough statistics,
تقديرا لإحصاءات وزارة الخارجية (الأمريكية) التقريبية،
there are about 800,000 -- 10 times the number --
هناك 800,000 -- عشر مرات ضعف الرقم --
that are trafficked across international borders.
تم نقلهم والإتجار بهم عبر الحدود الدولية.
And that does not even include those
وهذا لا يشمل حتى أولئك الذين
that are trafficked within country borders,
يتم نقلهم داخل حدود البلد نفسه،
which is a substantial portion.
وهو عدد أكبر.
And if you look at
ولو أنكم نظرتم إلى
another factor, another contrast,
عامل آخر، على النقيض،
a slave back then is worth
العبد في وقتها كان يساوي
about $40,000
ما يقارب 40,000 دولار
in today's money.
من قيمة النقود الحالية.
Today, you can buy a girl trafficked
اليوم، بإمكانك شراء فتاة تم تهريبها
for a few hundred dollars,
نظير القليل من مئات الدولارات،
which means she's actually more disposable.
وهو الأمر الذي يعني أنها في المتناول بوفرة ويمكن التخلص منها بسهولة.
But you know, there is progress being made
ولكن تعلمون، هناك تقدم يحدث
in places like Cambodia and Thailand.
في أماكن مثل كمبوديا وتايلند.
We don't have to expect a world
لا يجب علينا أن نتوقع عالما
where girls are bought and sold or killed.
تباع فيه الفتيات ويشترين أو يقتلن.
The second item on the agenda
العنصر الثاني على القائمة
is maternal mortality.
هو نسبة وفيات الأمهات.
You know, childbirth in this part of the world
تعلمون، ولادة طفل في هذا الجزء من العالم
is a wonderful event.
هو حدث مذهل.
In Niger, one in seven women
في النيجر، واحدة من كل سبع نساء
can expect to die during childbirth.
يتوقع أن تتوفى خلال ولادتها لطفل.
Around the world,
حول العالم،
one woman dies every minute and a half from childbirth.
هناك امرأة تموت كل دقيقة ونصف بسبب الولادة.
You know, it's not as though
تعلمون، ليس كما لو أننا
we don't have the technological solution,
لا نملك الحلول التقنية،
but these women have three strikes against them:
ولكن هناك ثلاثة عوامل ضد هؤلاء النساء:
they are poor, they are rural
هن فقيرات، هن يسكن أماكن قروية
and they are female.
وهن نساء.
You know, for every woman who does die,
تعلمون، لكل امرأة تموت،
there are 20 who survive
هناك 20 امرأة ينجين
but end up with an injury.
ولكن ينتهين بإصابة.
And the most devastating injury
والإصابة الأكثر تدميرا لهم
is obstetric fistula.
هي الناسور الولادي.
It's a tearing during obstructed labor
وهو تمزق يحدث أثناء الولادة المتعسرة
that leaves a woman incontinent.
يترك المرأة عاجزة عن التحكم بالإخراج (سلس مزمن).
Let me tell you about Mahabuba.
دعوني أخبركم عن محبوبة.
She lives in Ethiopia.
هي تعيش في إثيوبيا.
She was married against her will at age 13.
تزوجت رغم إرادتها في سن الثالثة عشرة.
She got pregnant, ran to the bush to have the baby,
عندما حملت، هرعت للأحراش لتنجب طفلها،
but you know, her body was very immature,
ولكن، تعلمون جسدها كان غير ناضج،
and she ended up having obstructed labor.
وانتهى بها الأمر أن تعسرت ولادتها.
The baby died, and she ended up with a fistula.
مات الطفل، وأصيبت هي بالناسور.
So that meant she was incontinent;
وهذا كان يعني أنها أصبحت مصابة بالسلس;
she couldn't control her wastes.
لم تستطع التحكم في فضلاتها.
In a word, she stank.
بإختصار، كانت تنفث الرائحة الكريهة.
The villagers thought she was cursed; they didn't know what to do with her.
سكان القرية اعتقدوا أنها أصيبت بلعنة; لم يعرفوا ما الذي سيفعلوه بها.
So finally, they put her at the edge of the village in a hut.
وأخيرا، وضعوها في كوخ على طرف القرية.
They ripped off the door
قاموا بنزع الباب
so that the hyenas would get her at night.
لأجل أن تتخلص منها الضباع في الليل.
That night, there was a stick in the hut.
تلك الليلة، كان هناك عصا من الخشب في الكوخ.
She fought off the hyenas with that stick.
محبوبة حاربت الضباع بهذه العصا.
And the next morning,
وفي الصباح التالي،
she knew if she could get to a nearby village where there was a foreign missionary,
علمت أنها إن وصلت للقرية القريبة حيث توجد إرسالية تبشير أجنبية
she would be saved.
فإنها ستنقذ.
Because she had some damage to her nerves,
ولأنها أصيبت بالتلف في أعصاب حركتها،
she crawled all the way -- 30 miles --
زحفت الطريق كله -- 30 ميلا --
to that doorstep, half dead.
حتى أعتاب الإرسالية، شبه ميتة.
The foreign missionary opened the door,
الإرسالية فتحت أبوابها،
knew exactly what had happened,
وعرفوا تماما ما حدث،
took her to a nearby fistula hospital in Addis Ababa,
أخذوها للمستشفى القريب الخاص بحالات الناسور في أديس أبابا،
and she was repaired
وتمت معالجتها
with a 350-dollar operation.
بعملية لاتتجاوز تكلفتها 350 دولارا.
The doctors and nurses there noticed
الأطباء والممرضات هناك لاحظوا
that she was not only a survivor,
أنها ليست ناجية وحسب،
she was really clever, and they made her a nurse.
كانت ذكية للغاية، لذا عينوها كممرضة.
So now, Mahabuba,
وإذن الآن، محبوبة،
she is saving the lives
تنقذ حياة
of hundreds, thousands, of women.
مئات، بل آلاف النساء.
She has become part of the solution, not the problem.
هي أصبحت جزءا من الحل، لا المشكلة.
She's moved out of a vicious cycle
تمكنت من الخروج من الحلقة المفرغة
and into a virtuous cycle.
لتدخل في حلقة مثمرة.
I've talked about some of the challenges,
لقد تحدثت عن بعض التحديات،
let me talk about some of the solutions,
دعني أتحدث عن بعض الحلول،
and there are predictable solutions.
هناك الحلول التي من السهل التنبؤ بها.
I've hinted at them: education
وقد ألمحت بهم: التعليم
and also economic opportunity.
وأيضا الفرص الاقتصادية.
So of course, when you educate a girl,
إذن بالطبع، حينما تعلم فتاة،
she tends to get married later on in life,
ستميل لأن تتزوج في مرحلة متأخرة من حياتها،
she tends to have kids later on in life, she tends to have fewer kids,
تميل لإنجاب الأطفال لاحقا، تميل لإنجاب أطفال أقل،
and those kids that she does have,
وهؤلاء الأطفال الذين تنجبهم،
she educates them in a more enlightened fashion.
تعلمهم بطريقة مستنيرة أكثر.
With economic opportunity,
الفرص الاقتصادية،
it can be transformative.
بإمكانها أن تغير الحياة تماما.
Let me tell you about Saima.
دعني أخبركم عن صائمة.
She lives in a small village outside Lahore, Pakistan.
هي تعيش في قرية صغيرة خارج لاهور، باكستان.
And at the time, she was miserable.
وفي ذاك الوقت، كانت بائسة.
She was beaten every single day
كانت تُضرب كل يوم
by her husband, who was unemployed.
على يد زوجها، الذي كان عاطلا عن العمل.
He was kind of a gambler type -- and unemployable, therefore --
كان من النوع المقامر -- ولأجل هذا، لم يكن أحد ليعرض عليه العمل--
and took his frustrations out on her.
وكان يلقي بإحباطه عليها.
Well, when she had her second daughter,
عندما رزقت ببنتها الثانية،
her mother in-law told her son,
حماتها قالت للزوج (ولدها)،
"I think you'd better get a second wife.
"أعتقد أنه من الأفضل أن تتزوج بزوجة ثانية.
Saima's not going to produce you a son."
صائمة لن تنجب لك ولدا".
This is when she had her second daughter.
كان هذا عندما أنجبت البنت الثانية.
At the time, there was
ذاك الوقت، كان هناك
a microlending group in the village
مجموعة إقراض تمنح القروض الصغيرة في القرية
that gave her a 65-dollar loan.
والذين أعطوها قرضا بقيمة 65 دولار.
Saima took that money,
صائمة أخذت النقود،
and she started an embroidery business.
وبدأت مشروع تطريز.
The merchants liked her embroidery; it sold very well,
التجار أعجبهم تطريزها; كان مرغوبا بشكل كبير،
and they kept asking for more.
لذا أخذوا يطلبون المزيد.
And when she couldn't produce enough,
حينما لم تتمكن من الإنتاج بشكل كافٍ،
she hired other women in the village.
وظفت نساء أخريات من قريتها.
Pretty soon she had 30 women in the village
وبوقت قياسي كان لديها 30 امرأة في القرية
working for her embroidery business.
يعملون في التطريز لحسابها.
And then,
وبعدها،
when she had to transport all of the embroidery goods
عندما اضطرت لنقل كل السلع المطرزة
from the village to the marketplace,
من القرية إلى السوق،
she needed someone to help her do the transport,
احتاجت لشخص يساعدها في الشحن،
so she hired her husband.
ولأجل هذا وظفت زوجها.
So now they're in it together.
وهم إذن يعملون معا.
He does the transportation and distribution,
هو يقوم بالشحن والتوزيع،
and she does the production and sourcing.
وهي تقوم بالإنتاج وجمع المصادر.
And now they have a third daughter,
والآن لديهم طفلة ثالثة،
and the daughters, all of them, are being tutored in education
والآن جميع بناتهم يحصلن على التعليم
because Saima knows what's really important.
لأن صائمة تعرف تماما ما هو المهم.
Which brings me to the final element, which is education.
والذي يقودني للعنصر الأخير، وهو التعليم.
Larry Summers, when he was chief economist at the World Bank,
لاري سمرز، عندما كان كبير اقتصاديي البنك العالمي،
once said that, "It may well be
قال مرة، "قد يكون من المؤكد
that the highest return on investment
أن أعلى مردود للاستثمار
in the developing world
في العالم النامي
is in girls' education."
هو في تعليم الفتيات".
Let me tell you about Beatrice Biira.
دعني أخبركم عن بياتريس بييرا.
Beatrice was living in Uganda
بياتريس كانت تعيش في أوغندا
near the Congo border,
على الحدود مع الكونغو،
and like Dai Manju, she didn't go to school.
وتماما مثل داي مانجو، لم تذهب للمدرسة.
Actually, she had never been to school,
في الواقع، هي لم تدخل المدرسة مطلقا،
not to a lick, one day.
ولا ليوم واحد حتى.
Her parents, again, said,
أبواها قالا، الشيء نفسه مجددا،
"Why should we spend the money on her?
"لم ينبغي علينا أن ننفق المال عليها؟
She's going to spend most of her life lugging water back and forth."
طالما سينتهي بها الأمر ممضية حياتها في نقل الماء جيئة وذهابا".
Well, it just so happens, at that time,
وقد صادف أنه، وقتها،
there was a group in Connecticut
كانت هناك مجموعة في كينكت
called the Niantic Community Church Group in Connecticut.
تدعى مجموعة مجتمع كنيسة نيانتيك.
They made a donation to an organization
قاموا بالتبرع لمنظمة
based in Arkansas
مقرها في أركنساس
called Heifer International.
تدعى هايفر العالمية.
Heifer sent two goats to Africa.
هايفر أرسلت شاتين إلى أفريقيا.
One of them ended up with Beatrice's parents,
وإحداهن انتهي بها الأمر لتصل لوالدي بياتريس.
and that goat had twins.
وأنجبت الشاة توائما.
The twins started producing milk.
والتوائم أخذوا في إنتاج الحليب.
They sold the milk for cash.
والأسرة باعت الحليب بمقابل النقود.
The cash started accumulating,
وبدأ المال في الإزدياد،
and pretty soon the parents said,
وبعدها بفترة بسيطة قال الأبوان،
"You know, we've got enough money. Let's send Beatrice to school."
"لدينا المال. دعنا نرسل بياتريس للمدرسة".
So at nine years of age,
ولذا في عمر التاسعة،
Beatrice started in first grade --
بياتريس بدأت الصف الأول --
after all, she'd never been to a lick of school --
حيث أنها لم تتلق أي تعليم سابق --
with a six year-old.
بجوار أقرانها الذين هم في عمر السادسة.
No matter, she was just delighted to be in school.
ولكن برغم هذا، كانت متحمسة لوجودها في المدرسة.
She rocketed to the top of her class.
وسرعان ما أصبحت الأولى على صفها.
She stayed at the top of her class
وبقيت الأولى على صفها
through elementary school, middle school,
طوال المراحل الإبتدائية، المتوسطة،
and then in high school,
ومن ثم الثانوية،
she scored brilliantly on the national examinations
كانت درجاتها متفوقة في الاختبارات الوطنية،
so that she became the first person in her village,
لدرجة أنها أصبحت أول شخص في قريتها
ever, to come to the United States
يأتي للولايات المتحدة
on scholarship.
في منحة دراسية.
Two years ago,
منذ عامين مضيا،
she graduated from Connecticut College.
تخرجت من كلية كينكت.
On the day of her graduation,
في يوم تخرجها،
she said, "I am the luckiest girl alive
قالت، "أنا أكثر فتاة محظوظة على الإطلاق
because of a goat."
بسبب شاة".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that goat was $120.
وتلك الشاة كانت تساوي 120 دولارا.
So you see how transformative
بإمكانكم أن تروا كم هو محولة للحياة
little bits of help can be.
هي تلك المساعدات الصغيرة.
But I want to give you a reality check.
ولكنني أريد أن أمنحكم صورة من أرض الواقع.
Look: U.S. aid, helping people is not easy,
حسنا، المساعدات الأمريكية، مساعدة الناس ليست بالأمر السهل.
and there have been books that have criticized U.S. aid.
هناك كتب انتقدت المساعدات الأمريكية.
There's Bill Easterly's book.
هناك كتاب بيل ايسترلي.
There's a book called "Dead Aid."
هناك كتاب عنوانه "المساعدة الميتة".
You know, the criticism is fair;
تعلمون، النقد كان عادلا;
it isn't easy.
لأن الأمر ليس سهلا.
You know, people say how
تعلمون، الناس تتساءل كيف
half of all water well projects, a year later, are failed.
نصف مشاريع آبار المياه، تفشل بعد سنة.
When I was in Zimbabwe,
عندما كنت في زيمبابوي،
we were touring a place with the village chief --
كنا نجوب منطقة مع عمدة القرية --
he wanted to raise money for a secondary school --
هو أراد جمع المال من أجل مدرسة ثانوية --
and there was some construction a few yards away,
وكان هناك بعض أعمال الإنشاء على بعد عدة ياردات،
and I said, "What's that?"
وأنا قلت، "ماهو ذلك؟"
He sort of mumbled.
هو نوعا ما أخذ يتمتم.
Turns out that it's a failed irrigation project.
اتضح أنه مشروع
A few yards away was a failed chicken coop.
على بعد عدة ياردات كان هناك مشروع مزرعة دواجن لم تكتمل.
One year, all the chickens died, and no one wanted to put the chickens in there.
في إحدى السنوات، كل الدجاج نفق، ولا أحد أراد أن يضع دجاجاته هناك.
It's true, but we think that you don't through the baby out with the bathwater;
هذا يحدث، لكننا نعتقد أنه لا يجب أن نرمي الطفل في ماء السباحة (ونتوقع منه أن يسبح);
you actually improve.
أنتم في الواقع تتطورون.
You learn from your mistakes, and you continuously improve.
تتعلمون من أخطاءكم، وتتطورون بشكل مستمر.
We also think that individuals
أيضا نعتقد أن الأفراد
can make a difference, and they should,
بإمكانهم صنع الفارق، وينبغي أن يصنعوا هذا الفارق،
because individuals, together,
لأننا الأفراد، مجتمعين،
we can all help create a movement.
نستطيع كلنا المساهمة في خلق حركة.
And a movement of men and women
والحركة المؤلفة من الرجال والنساء
is what's needed to bring about social change,
هي ما نحتاجه لنجلب التغيير في المجتمع،
change that will address
التغيير الذي سيستهدف
this great moral challenge.
هذا التحدي الأخلاقي الكبير.
So then, I ask,
إذن، اتساءل;
what's in it for you?
ما المنفعة العائدة عليك؟
You're probably asking that. Why should you care?
ربما أنتم تسألون هذا. لم علينا أن نهتم؟
I will just leave you with two things.
أنا فقط سأترككم مع شيئين.
One is that research shows
الأول هو أن الأبحاث أظهرت
that once you have
هو أنك بمجرد أن
all of your material needs taken care of --
تكون كل احتياجاتك المادية مستوفاة --
which most of us, all of us, here in this room do --
وهو الأمر الحاصل بالنسبة لأغلبنا، أو لنقل كلنا هنا في هذه القاعة --
research shows that
الأبحاث أظهرت أن
there are very few things in life
هناك أشياء قليلة في الحياة
that can actually elevate your level of happiness.
بإمكانها فعليا أن ترفع معدلات سعادتكم.
One of those things
واحد من هذه الأشياء
is contributing to a cause larger than yourself.
هو المساهمة في قضية أكبر منكم كأفراد.
And the second thing,
والشيء الآخر.
it's an anecdote that I'll leave you with.
هو حكاية سأترككم معها.
And that is the story
وهذه هي قصة
of an aid worker in Darfur.
إحدى العاملات في المساعدات في دارفور.
Here was a woman
كان ثمة هذه المرأة
who had worked in Darfur,
التي عملت في دارفور،
seeing things that no human being should see.
ورأت أشياء لا يجب لأي إنسان أن يراها.
Throughout her time there,
خلال الوقت الذي أمضته هناك،
she was strong, she was steadfast.
كانت قوية، وكانت ثابتة.
She never broke down.
لم تنهار أبدا.
And then she came back to the United States
ومن ثم عادت إلى الولايات المتحدة
and was on break, Christmas break.
لإمضاء عطلة، عطلة عيد الميلاد.
She was in her grandmother's backyard,
كانت في الفناء الخلفي بمنزل جدتها،
and she saw something that made her break down in tears.
عندما رأت شيئا جعلها تشرع بالبكاء.
What that was
وهذا الشيء كان
was a bird feeder.
منصة إطعام الطيور.
And she realized that she had the great fortune
هي أدركت كم تمتلك من الحظ
to be born in a country
لتكون ولدت في دولة
where we take security for granted,
حيث نعتبر الأمن فيها من المسلمات،
where we not only can feed, clothe
وحيث لا نستطيع فيها أن نطعم، نكسو،
and house ourselves,
ونؤوي أنفسنا وحسب،
but also provide for wild birds
وإنما نعيل الطيور البرية
so they don't go hungry in the winter.
لأجل ألا يجوعوا في الشتاء.
And she realized that with that great fortune
وهي أدركت أن مع النعمة العظيمة
comes great responsibility.
تأتي مسئولية كبيرة.
And so, like her,
وإذن، تماما مثلها،
you, me,
أنت، أنا،
we have all won the lottery of life.
نحن كلنا ربحنا يانصيب الحياة.
And so the question becomes:
والآن يصبح السؤال:
how do we discharge that responsibility?
كيف نسدد هذا الدين وهذه المسئولية؟
So, here's the cause.
إذن، إليكم القضية.
Join the movement.
انضموا للحركة.
Feel happier and help save the world.
كونوا أسعد وساعدوا في إنقاذ العالم.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)